Finding Aid for the Tulancingo (Hildago, Mexico) Manuscript Collection, 1567-1882 LSC.2073
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Post-1852 manuscripts, 1854-1877; 5 boxes
  - [Petition requesting verbal judgment for money in a civil matter between Manuel Arroyo on behalf of José Luciano Moñtano and Don Sanchez Hidalgo, as executor for Don Luís Calla], 1872; 2 leaves (Box 6, Folder 18)
    Petition includes statements from both parties indicating that the dispute pertains to certain obligations for heads of cattle and backrents owed on a ranch in San Nicolas.
  - Ynsidente del juicio ejecutivo que el representante de la hacienda pública del Estado siguiÓ contra el C. Vicente Vera Gomez sobre pago de contribuciones., 1872-1873; 9 leaves (Box 6, Folder 19)
    Legal documents and petitions pertaining to a civil suit in the entitled matter Public State Treasury versus Vicente Vera Gomez for failure to pay honorariums or fees. File includes a balance sheet outlining legal fees and expenses in the entitled case.
  - Ejecutivo: El abogado representante de D[o]n Ygnacio Moreno Leon, contra D[o]n Antonio Amador, 1870-1872; 10 leaves (Box 6, Folder 20)
    Legal documents in the civil suit entitled: attorney representing Don Ygnacio Moreno Leon versus against Don Antonio Amador. File includes a power of attorney granted in favor of Gabriel Ormaechea by Ygnacio Moreno Leon, an account draft dated 1870.
  - Juicio civil ordinario sobre pesos promovido por el Abogado representante de Don Francisco Montez contra Don Antonio Amador, 1868-1873; 34 leaves (Box 6, Folder 21)
    Judgment in an ordinary civil suit over money furthered by Don Francisco Montez, represented by his attorney, versus Don Antonio Amador. File includes interrogatories, petitions, a promissory note dated 1868, and a letter from the defendant to plaintiff.
  - Sobre la clase de quiebra de Don Marciano Castro; Don José Haro, contra Don Marciano Castro, sobre pesos, 1872-1873; 17 leaves (Box 6, Folder 22)
    Documents relating to the bankruptcy of merchant Marciano Castro. Petition indicates Don Marciano Castro was threatened with possible liquidation in order to satisfy a possible judgment in favor of José Haro, also a merchant.
  - Autos del intestado de D[oñ]a Teofila Nava, 1872-1873; 28 leaves (Box 6, Folder 23)
    Probate documents relating to the intestacy of Doña Teofila Nava. File includes petitions, interrogatories, an estate inventory of assets referencing the property known as "La Moñtañesa," and an accounting of debts. Decedent was the owner of a cigarette [company].
  - Juicio sumario sobre alimentos promobido p[o]r Eulalia García contra el C. Manuel Gonzalez Bereztain [Beristain], 1872; 18 leaves (Box 6, Folder 24)
    Summary judgment for alimony furthered by Eulalia García versus Manuel Gonzalez Bereztain. Petitioner García indicated that she had recently given birth to an infant child fathered by Manuel Beristain and that he had failed to provide for them.
  - Inventario a bienes de D[o]n Catarino Escorcia, 1872-1873; 5 leaves (Box 6, Folder 25)
    Probate documents including an inventory of goods for the estate of Don Catarino Escorcia. Documents reflect that Don Catarino Escorcia's widow, Antonia Alarcon, has been named executor of the estate and guardian of their minor children.
  - Los C. C. Luís Gonzalez y Aurelio Meneses sobre pesos [and also] El C. Aurelio Meneses recusando al C. Juez de 1a [primera] Inst[anci]a del Distrito, 1872 only; 13 leaves (Box 6, Folder 26)
    Civil suit for money in an action between merchants Aurelio Meneses and José Haros. A dispute arose over monies allegedly owed to José Haros. Defendant's business was threatened with possible liquidation in order to satisfy the judgment demanded by plaintiff.
  - Oficio Publico, registro de Hipotecas, a cargo de José María García - testimonio de la transacion celebrada entre los C. C. Miguel Arroyo y Valeriano Linarte sobre la propiedad de un capital legado por la finada Señora Doña Soledad Leon, 1872; 8 leaves (Box 6, Folder 27)
    Legal documents and petitions pertaining to a property that was the subject of an earlier arbitration dispute between the entitled parties dated 1869. The disputed property was supposed to fund a chaplaincy in accordance with an earlier promise by decedent.
  - Diligencias practicadas para hacer efectija la multa de setecientos treinta y seis pesos impuesta á Don Juan BengÓa y á la S[eño]ra Doña Joséfa García de Ruiz, 1872; 5 leaves (Box 6, Folder 28)
    Legal documents pertaining to a fine imposed upon Don Juan BengÓa and Doña María Joséfa García de Ruiz.
  - Sobre comiso de un cargamento de chilpotle, 1872; 5 leaves (Box 6, Folder 29)
    Documents pertaining to the seizure of an illegal shipment of chipotle chile that was discovered being transported by donkey.
  - Oficio Publico, registro de Hipotecas, a cargo de José María García - testimonio y ultimo voluntad del testamento y ...del Señor Don Luís Chavez, 1872-1873; 38 leaves (Box 6, Folder 30)
    Probate documents pertaining to the estate of Don Luís Chavez, including his last will and testament, inventory of assets, petitions, municipal rent receipts, and other legal documents. Documents indicate that the decedent was twice married.
  - El C. Octaviano Galarza, pidiendo se levante el aseguramiento de unos efectos de abarrotes, 1872; 7 leaves (Box 6, Folder 31)
    Petition by Octaviano Galarza, a merchant, seeking the return of his property and effects. Petition includes an inventory of the disputed items.
  - Don Tomas Urrutia contra D[o]n Victoriano Yarto sobre pesos, 1871-1873; 25 leaves (Box 6, Folder 32)
    Civil suit over money in the entitled matter Tomas Urrutia versus Victoriano Yarto. Petitioner Tomas Urrutia alleged that Victoriano Yarto owed $314 pesos, 44 centavos.
  - Intestado del Ciudadano José María Várgas, 1872; 4 leaves (Box 6, Folder 33)
    Probate documents for intestate José María Várgas. Documents indicate that decedent left behind a widow, Doña María Ygnacia García, who submitted a petition contesting the intestacy of the estate.
  - Juicio verbal sobre pago de honorario que demanda el C. Dr. Ramon Galan al C. José Dionicio Soto, 1872; 20 leaves (Box 6, Folder 34)
    Civil suit demanding payment for travel expenses and medical treatment rendered by Dr. Ramon Galan in the entitled action Dr. Ramon Galan versus José Dionicio Soto. File includes petitions, interrogatories, and other legal documents.
  - Don José M[ari]a Galindo renunciando la tutela de los hijos menores de Doña Joséfa Ruiz, 1859--1872; 11 leaves (Box 6, Folder 35)
    Petitions and legal documents pertaining to the legal guardianship of the Ruiz children, minor children of Rafael Ruiz and Doña Joséfa Ruiz. File contains a petition dated 1859 announcing the earlier appointment of Don José María Galindo as executor.
  - Juicio de Hacienda contra Don Antonio Arce, por la introducion de un ganado, 1872; 12 leaves (Box 6, Folder 36)
    Civil suit against Don Antonio Arce regarding a dispute over his ability to sell livestock.
  - Don Marcos Lechuga, y Doña Florentina Marquez, reconociendo a un hijo de ambos llamado Juan., 1872; 4 leaves (Box 6, Folder 37)
    Legal documents indicate that Marcos Lechuga and Florentina Marquez had illicit relations, that a child named Gregorio was the result of this relationship, and that the father legally recognized his son.
  - Don Ygnacio Lechuga contra Doña Anastacia Reyes sobre pesos, 1872; 6 leaves (Box 6, Folder 38)
    Civil suit over money in the entitled matter Don Ygnacio Lechuga versus Anastacia Reyes.
  - Don Ygnacio Urquijo eponiendose a un embargo mandado practicar por un juez de lo civil de Mexico, en la Hac[ien]da de S[an] Andres, 1872; 7 leaves (Box 6, Folder 39)
    Petition by Don Ygnacio Urquijo opposing an order for an appraisal of the ranch at San Andres pursuant to a mandate from a civil judge. The ranch in question had formerly been the property of General Francisco Pérez who died intestate.
  - [Legal documents and petitions for matters involving the estate of Juan Amador], 1872; 8 leaves (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Posecion judicial del Rancho de Santa M[ari]a del Municipio de Acatlan dada p[o]r el C. Lic. José de la Paz...Juez de 1a [primera] Inst[anci]a de este Distrito al C. Man[ue]l Soto Duran, 1872; 10 leaves (Box 6, Folder 41)
    Documents memorializing the purchase of the property Rancho de Santa María in the municipality of Acatlan, introduced by Manuel Soto Duran, executor of the estate of Mariano Soto, his father.
  - [Probate documents for Doña Soledad Olvera], 1872; 3 leaves (Box 6, Folder 42)
    Will and testament of Doña Soledad Olvera and related probate documents. The will and testament reflects that Doña Soledad Olvera named her brother, José María Olvera, as executor. Petition submitted by José María Olvera notifed the court of the death.
  - [Probate documents for Mariano Martinez], 1872; 10 leaves (Box 6, Folder 43)
    Probate documents for the estate of Mariano Martinez. Luís Martinez, decedent's son, was appointed executor. File includes an estate inventory of assets.
  - Poder general otorgado por María Guadalupe Feliciana en favor del Ciudadano Licenciado José María Lezama, 1872; 7 leaves (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Documents submitted by María Guadalupe Feliciana, a widow and resident of the rancheria at San Pedrito, granting power of attorney to José María Lezama.
  - Interdicto de obra nueva los ciudadanos José M[arí]a Chavez y Cristobal Cabrera contra el C. Manuel Fernandez, 1869-1882; 57 leaves (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Civil case in the entitled matter José María Chavez and Cristobal Cabrera versus Manuel Fernandez. Case involved allegations over water damage to property due to a construction project undertaken by Manuel Fernandez.
  - [Probate documents for the estate of Norbert Escorcia], 1872-1873; 31 leaves (Box 7, Folder 3)
    José María Escorcia, decedent's brother, was executor of the estate. File includes an estate inventory of assets and debts, a notice to the court of Norbert Escorcia's death due to a pulmonary condition, and receipts of payment made by José María Escorcia.
  - Tercería a dominio interpuesta por el C. Mig[ue]l Sanchez Hidalgo y hermanas en el juicio ejecutivo que sobre pesos sigue el C. Mariano Ponce contra el C. Lic. Mig[ue]l Sanchez Hidalgo, 1874-1875; 104 leaves (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Arbitration proceeding stemming from an unpaid mortgage in a civil matter entitled: Mariano Ponce versus Manuel Sanchez Hidalgo, and a countersuit by Miguel and sisters Romana, Guadalupe, and Manuela Sanchez Hidalgo against Mariano Ponce.
  - Particion de los bienes del difunto D[on] Balentin Romero, 1864-1872; 9 leaves (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Probate documents for the estate of Don Valentin Romero. Executor of the estate was Nicolas Gea. File includes a petition regarding the division of assets, the last will and testament of Don Valentin Romero dated 1864, and an estate inventory.
  - Testimonio de la escritura de hipoteca de cuatro terrenos y dos casas otorgada por los ciudadanos Manuel Marquez Obiedo [Oviedo] y Miguel Romero a favor del Señor Don Tomas Urrutia, 1872-1874; 30 leaves (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Testimony concerning a civil dispute over a notarized mortgage agreement for four land plots and two houses agreed upon by residents Manuel Marquez Obiedo and Miguel Romero in favor of Don Tomas Urrutia. File includes a balance sheet, petitions, receipts.
  - Testimonio del testamento otorgado por la Señora Doña Catarina García de Gonzalez en los terminos que dentro se expresan; [and] Foja a la testamentaria de la S[eño]ra D[oñ]a Catarina García de Gonzalez, 1872; 37 leaves (Box 7, Folder 7)
    Probate documents for the estate of Catarina García de Gonzalez. File includes her will and testament, notice to the court of her death, and other documents. Documents indicate that decedent named her husband, Manuel Gonzalez Barona, executor of her estate.
  - Juicio verbal el C. José Soledad García contra el C. José Morgado sobre pesos, 1873; 4 leaves (Box 7, Folder 8)
    Civil suit involving a financial dispute between José Soledad García versus José Morgado.
  - Acta de juicio verbal sobre pesos, D[on] Luís Bladinieres contra D[on] Enrique Pontal, 1872-1873; 9 leaves (Box 7, Folder 9)
    Petitions and legal documents pertaining to a dispute among merchants over monies owed.
  - [Juicio arbitral que sigue con Don Antonio Gayol sobre liquidacion de cuentas], 1873-1874; 37 leaves (Box 7, Folder 10)
    Numerous petitions, legal documents, correspondence, and a balance sheet relating to an arbitration judgment requiring the settlement of accounts by Antonio Gayol, and his associate Tomas Urrutia, in a commercial matter involving the ironworks.
  - Juicio de alimentos: Diligencias practicadas a pedimento de D[oñ]a Francisca Várgas solicitando que por providencia precautoria se asegun una cantidad de pesos perteneciente a la herencia de su marido Agustin Olvera, 1873; 9 leaves (Box 7, Folder 11)
    Documents relating to a demand for alimony by Doña Francisca Várgas against Agustin Olvera, her husband. File includes documents in the entitled caption: "Juicio sumario sobre alimentos, D[oñ]a Francisca Várgas demandandos los a su esposo D. Agustin Olvera
  - Intestado de D[oñ]a Bartola Batalla, 1874-1876; 9 leaves (Box 7, Folder 12)
    Probate documents relating to the intestacy of Bartola Batalla.
  - Sobre pesos promovido p[o]r la Sociedad Pontal y Cavade contra Don Vicente Morales, 1871-1875; 9 leaves (Box 7, Folder 13)
    Civil suit involving a demand by Pontal and Cavade versus Vicente Morales for repayment of monies owed to them.
  - [Civil suit over money initiated by Ygnacio Moreno Leon through his attorney Gabriel Ormaechea versus Antonio Amador], 1872-1873; 4 leaves (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - El C. Luís G. Soto contra Don Ygn[aci]o Urquijo sobre pesos, 1872-1874; 19 leaves (Box 7, Folder 15)
    Civil suit initiated by Luís G. Soto versus Ygnacio Urquijo demanding repayment for money borrowed. File includes interrogatories, petitions, and a letter dated 1872 signed by defendant Ygnacio Urquijo memorializing money received from Luís G. Soto.
  - Intestado del C. Vicente Chavez, 1874; 4 leaves (Box 7, Folder 16)
    Documents pertaining to the intestacy of Vicente Chavez. File consists of a declaration notifying the court of the death of Vicente Chavez Alarcon, and a declaration submitted by his widow, Doña Dolores Alarcon, contesting the intestacy of her husband.
  - El C. Lic. José M[ari]a Carvajal como apoderado de Don Juan Rueda, contra D[o]n Agustin Madrid, sobre pesos, 1872-1874; 13 leaves (Box 7, Folder 17)
    Civil suit over money initiated by Spaniards Juan Rueda and Company through his legal representative José María Carvajal versus Agustin Madrid. Petitions indicate that plaintiffs sought to recover payment for an account draft owed by defendant Madrid.
  - Don Miguel de la Rosa produciendo la causa consignando una cantidad debida a Don Francisco Becerra, 1874; 6 leaves (Box 7, Folder 18)
    Civil suit by Miguel de la Rosa versus Francisco Becerra for money owed.
  - Don Andres Hernandez deduciendo derechos a los bienes de Doña Rosa Ruiz, 1874; 5 leaves (Box 7, Folder 19)
    Probate documents pertaining to the intestacy of Rosa Ruiz. File consists of petitions filed by Andres Hernandez, decedent's son, including a declaration submitted by a parish priest memorializing the existence of a baptismal record for Andres Hernandez
  - El C. Manuel Lagarreta pidiendo el testamento del finado C. Gregorio Hernandez, 1874; 7 leaves (Box 7, Folder 20)
    Petition filed by Manuel Lagarreta on behalf of his granddaughter seeking to obtain half of the estate assets of Gregorio Hernandez, her father, in accordance with his will.
  - Tercería interpuesta por el C. Ygnacio Muñez en el juicio ejecutivo promovido por el C. Lic. José M[arí]a Carvajal en representacion del C. José Oropeza contra el C. Jesus García Pérez, sobre pesos, 1874; 6 leaves (Box 7, Folder 21)
    Arbitration in a dispute by Ygnacio Muñez seeking seeking repayment for a mortgage owed by Jesus García y Pérez. José Oropeza appears to be a third party in the dispute. Both Oropeza and defendant Jesus García y Pérez were represented by José María Carv
  - [Declaration of fines and taxes imposed upon Apolonio Uribarri by the Custom's House], 1875; 2 leaves (Box 7, Folder 22)
    See Box 8, folders 4 through 6 for additional files on Apolonio Uribarri.
  - Los albaceas del finado D[o]n José María Morgado pidiendo licencia p[ar]a la formacion de inventarios, 1874; 7 leaves (Box 7, Folder 23)
    Probate documents pertaining to the estate of José María Morgado and a request by the executors of the estate to generate an estate inventory. File includes the notarized will and testament of José María Morgado indicating that his wife, Dominga Escorcia
  - Testimonio del poder especial otorgada por el C. Juan Huazo, a fabor del C. Lic. Francisco Rodriguez Madariaga, 1874; 38 leaves (Box 7, Folder 24)
    Civil suit in a financial dispute entitled Juan Huaza, a merchant, versus Ygnacio Urquijo. Juan Huaza, represented by Francisco Rodriguez Madariaga, alleged that Ygnacio Urquijo failed to fulfill the terms of a sales agreement. File includes petitions.
  - Testimonio del poder gra... conferido al C. Lic. Gabriel Orinaechea por los hermanos Gomez, 1874-1875; 5 leaves (Box 7, Folder 25)
    Probate petitions regarding the estate of José María Gomez submitted by his children Catarina Gomez, José Trinidad, and Pedro Gomez.
  - Prueba producido por el C. Lic. Gabriel Ormaechea en el juicio que sobre e...icio en una escritura de ha promovido a la S[eño]ra D[oñ]a Ramona Vergare de Ponce., 1874-1875; 13 leaves (Box 7, Folder 26)
    Interrogatories in a civil dispute between Ygnacio Urquijo, represented by his attorney Gabriel Ormaechea, versus Ramona Vergare de Ponce represented by Teofilo Ponce.
  - Verbal sobre pesos, promovido por el C. Lic. José M[ari]a Carvajal, como apoderado de los Señores Pontal y Cavade, contra el C. Agustin Madrid, 1871-1875; 42 leaves (Box 7, Folder 27)
    Civil suit in a financial dispute between merchants Señores Pontal and Cavade versus Agustin Madrid. Folder includes balance sheets, legal fees and expenses, petitions, and interrogatories. The dispute involved a business agreement among the merchants.
  - Ynventarios a bienes del Señor Presbitero Don Maccimo de German cura que fue de la Parroquia de Epazoyucan, 1874-1875; 41 leaves (Box 7, Folder 28)
    Probate documents including the will and testament for the estate of Maximo de German y Olvera, a priest from the Epazoyucan parish. File contains an itemized balance sheet of fees and legal expenses, estate inventory, list of estate debts, etc.
  - Juicio verbal promovido p[o]r el C. Vicente Dominguez contra el C. Ygn[aci]o Moreno Leon, sobre la entrega de una libranza, 1874; 10 leaves (Box 7, Folder 29)
    Verbal judgment furthered by Vicente Dominguez versus Ygnacio Moreno Leon regarding the entry of a mortgage.
  - Ejecutivo sobre p[eso]s el C. Vicente Hernandez contra el C. Jorge Alarcon, 1874; 6 leaves (Box 7, Folder 30)
    Civil suit over money by Vicente Hernandez versus Jorge Alarcon. Jorge Alarcon had borrowed $660 pesos from Vicente Hernandez and Hernandez sued to recover the loan. File includes the original letter signed by Alarcon memorializing the loan.
  - [Arbitration judgment involving Antonio Gayol and Tomas Urrutia; and also] Pruebas rendidas por el S[eñor] D[on] Ant[oni]o Gayol, 1872-1876; 118 leaves (Box 7, Folder 31)
    Arbitration documents involving Tomas Urrutia, Antonio Gayol, and others. Documents indicate that a partnership was formed in 1869 between Tomas Urrutia, Antonio Gayol, and Pedro Miguel Olazo to create Reyes iron works.
  - [Documents relating to the marriage separation between Felipe Saldivar and María Faustina Lira of the town of San Lorenzo], 1874; 4 leaves (Box 7, Folder 32)
    Documents indicate that María Faustina Lira initiated legal proceedings against her husband Felipe Saldivar due to mistreatment and discord during their marriage. Petition indicates that María Faustina Lira ended up in the hospital and her husband in jail.
  - Ynterdicto de depojo promovido por el C. Luís Rodriguez contra el C. José M[ari]a Olvera, 1874; 6 leaves (Box 7, Folder 33)
    Civil suit involving a property dispute and a violent confrontation alleged by Luís Rodriguez against José María Olvera. In his petition, Luís Rodriguez alleges that the defendant stripped him of his land with the aid of a gang of peons.
  - Sobre nombramiento de tutor a los hijos del finado C. Vicente Pérez, 1874; 6 leaves (Box 7, Folder 34)
    Petition by Pascuala Ybarra requesting that Francisco Pérez be named the guardian for the children of decedent Vicente Pérez. Pascuala Ybarra was the maternal grandmother for said minors, María Ynes and Carlota.
  - Testimonio del poder especial conferido al C. Lic. Fran[cis]co Rodriguez Madariaga por Don Claudio Durand, 1874; 24 leaves (Box 7, Folder 35)
    Power of attorney conferred upon Francisco Rodriguez Madariaga by Claudio Durand, a Frenchman and resident at the Trinidad iron foundry. Petitions reflect a property dispute arose between Claudio Durand and Mariano Villegas.
  - Intestado del incapacitado Don Trinidad Campos, 1874; 17 leaves (Box 7, Folder 36)
    Legal documents including a notice to the court of the death of José Agapito Campos and a petition by José Haro indicating that he had been the legal guardian and caretaker of José Agapito Campos who had become mentally incapacitated leading up to his death.
  - Division de los bienes que quedaron por fallecimiento del Señor C. Mariano Martinez, 1874; 14 leaves (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Probate documents for the estate of Mariano Martinez. First case file consists of an estate inventory and a petition submitted by Luís Martinez, executor of his father's estate. Documents reflect who the estate's legal heirs were.
  - Ynventarios a bienes de la finada Doña María Guadalupe Lira, 1846-1875; 40 leaves (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Probate documents for the estate of María Guadalupe Lira including an estate inventory and petitions by Antonio Lira, decedent's brother. Folder also contains the following case caption documents: "Intestado de Doña María Lira."
  - Testimonio del Poder conferido al C. Lic. Manuel Arroyo por el C. Ygnacio Hernandez, 1872-1874; 10 leaves (Box 8, Folder 3)
    Power of attorney conferred upon Manuel Arroyo by Ygnacio Hernandez to represent him in pursuit of repayment of a lien borrowed by Miguel Castro. File contains the original letter signed by Miguel Castro memorializing the terms of the lien.
  - Convenio celebrado por Don Apolonio Uribarri sus acreedores, 1875-1876; 28 leaves (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Documents of appraisal for the estate of Apolonio Uribarri in a bankruptcy proceeding, as well as petitions and other legal documents recognizing estate debts with the following creditors: Francisco Pérez Soto, José María Ponce, José San Vicente, etc.
  - Criminal. Contra D[on] Apolonio Uribarri por haber sido declarado en estado de quiebra, 1874-1876; 32 leaves (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Criminal suit against merchant Apolonio Uribarri relating to his bankruptcy.
  - Autos relativos a la quiebra a D[on] Apolonio Uribarri, 1874-1875; 66 leaves (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Documents relating to the bankruptcy of Apolonio Uribarri including petitions, a notarized power of attorney conferred upon Jose Maria Sanchez, balance sheets, and account drafts.
  - Intestado a D[o]n Francisco Hernandez a Rosa María Ruiz, 1874; 9 leaves (Box 8, Folder 7)
    Probate documents for Rosa María Ruiz and Francisco Hernandez consisting of petitions and declarations of existing death records filed by their sons, Andres and Bartolo Hernandez. Petitioners contest the intestacy of their parents.